# Patrick K. Martin

Phone: (401) 595-8552 • E-Mail: pkmartin82@gmail.com • LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/pkmartin82



### **SUMMARY**

As a software professional with over 17 years of technical and managerial experience, I have held key roles in multiple software disciplines. I have worked in all phases of the software development lifecycle and I have found my specialties in both microservice architectural design and leadership of business-critical teams.

## **EXPERIENCE**

## IT Manager II Nelnet Business Services Mar 2019 – Current

- Oversee three development teams with two management direct reports and over 20 indirect reports
- Responsible for building .NET microservice applications in an agile, CI/CD process
- Direct development efforts to replace parts of monolithic legacy applications with microservices
- Lead development initiative integrating ServiceNow ticket creation from Azure DevOps pipelines
- Subject Matter Expert for Data Center Migration project, including server, application and tooling moves
- Coordinate development efforts with Product, Operations, Finance, and Compliance departments
- Present biweekly demonstrations of newly deployed functionality
- Coordinator for IT Conference and Hackathon events

### **Director, Application Development**

# **Tuition Management Systems**

Sept 2017 - March 2019

- Director of three IT departments: Quality Assurance, Production Support, Release Engineering
- Managed six direct and five indirect reports at multiple locations
- Proven success in building high-performing, multi-functional teams
- Championed DevOps and Continuous Improvement culture and values throughout organization
- Incorporated IT Operations into Agile practices, like daily standups, sprint/release planning, retrospectives
- Organized Release Engineering duties for 80+ Java and .NET applications and 20+ VB6/COM+ applications
- Assured application quality via manual and automated testing through Selenium Webdriver, Katalon, SQL
- Provided architectural input to development initiatives, specifically microservice design and function
- Coordinated and supported job scheduling operations using Control-M Framework
- Reduced Post-Release defects by over 50% by instituting organization-wide regression testing effort
- Revamped, automated and increased frequency of server patching process

### Manager, Application Development

### **Tuition Management Systems**

Oct 2014 - Sept 2017

- Manager of two IT departments: Quality Assurance and Production Support
- Managed nine direct reports at multiple locations, plus contract developers and outside consultants
- Introduced Selenium IDE and Webdriver Automated Frameworks to QA staff
- Created a rapid triage, investigation and fix-deployment process used after major releases to production
- Implemented priority-based system to triage, resolve and escalate production application support tickets
- Coordinated integration of a new microservice with outside vendor to add text messaging capabilities
- Experienced with Payment Card Industry (PCI) audits
- Interviewed and onboarded new employees / participated in employee turnover

#### **Senior Software Developer**

# Tuition Management Systems Ju

June 2012 - Oct 2014

- Scrum Master and Lead Developer of a web application integrating TMS suite with remote client systems
- Lead Developer of a microservice integrating with Verizon's Interactive Voice Response (IVR) system
- Client-facing IT representative in support-calls/marketing initiatives with both vendors and clients

# Patrick K. Martin





### **Senior Software Engineer**

### Raytheon Co.

July 2005 - June 2012

- Completed all phases of the software development lifecycle for both distributed system infrastructure and graphical user interface software for Zumwalt-class US Navy surface ships
- Performed enterprise-level system integration testing of Zumwalt software with US Navy Technical Team
- Elected President of the Young Employee Support Network; coordinated events for new-hire acclimation

### **EDUCATION**

#### Master of Business Administration

# University of Rhode Island

Fall 2009 - Summer 2011

- Cumulative GPA: 3.78
- Degree Focus in Computer Science

### Bachelor of Science, Computer Engineering

- Cumulative GPA: 3.83, Summa Cum Laude
- Computer Engineering Salutatorian

# University of Rhode Island

Fall 2000 - Spring 2004

- Minored in Mathematics
- Tau Beta Pi, Phi Eta Sigma Honor Societies

Beta Gamma Sigma Honor Society

### **SKILLS**

- Crisis management: ability to quickly, clearly and confidently handle adverse emergency situations
- Motivating and engaging people
- Relaying technical information to non-technical audiences
- Public speaking
- Certified as a Raytheon Six Sigma Specialist

### **TECHNOLOGIES**

- Development Processes: Scrum, Agile, CI/CD
- Programming Languages: Java, .Net (C#), HTML, XML, SQL, JavaScript, Python, PowerShell, BASH, YAML
- Databases: SQL Server, MongoDB, Oracle, MySQL/MariaDB
- Cloud technologies: Azure DevOps, GitHub, DataDog, Kubernetes, AWS: IAM, Code Commit,
- Automated Testing Platforms: Junit/NUnit, Selenium, Katalon, Cypress, JMeter, Postman
- Release Engineering technologies: Git, YAML Pipelines, Octopus, Perforce, Mayen, MSBuild, AnthillPro
- Server Platforms: Experience developing in, configuring and supporting JBoss EAP, Microsoft IIS, Tomcat
- Server Patching Technologies: Ivanti (Windows), Satellite (Red Hat Enterprise Linux)
- Project / Defect Management Tools: Azure DevOps, Jira, Confluence, ServiceNow, Incident Monitor
- Job Scheduling Tools: Control-M, GECS
- Microsoft Office suite
- Operating Systems: Windows, Windows Server, Linux, MacOS